Hello.
The purpose of this section is to present the RFID technology in a very advanced way.
So what's RFID?
This radio frequency identification, or RFID, is a technology which is working on radio frequency
or radio waves.
So this technology is used to automatically identify the object or tracking the objects.
Now this object could be anything.
The objects could be books in library, or it could be any item which are purchasing from the shopping
mall.
Or it could be the inventory in the warehouse.
Or maybe it could be your own car.
And not only objects, it can be also used for tracking the animals.
So in this RFID technology, the RFID tag is used to get attached to the object which we want to track.
So this RFID reader is continuously sending radio waves.
So whenever this object is in the range of the reader, then this RFID tag will transmit its feedback
signal to the reader.
So it's very similar to the technology which is used in a barcode.
But in case of a barcode, the object and the scanner should be in line of sight.
As this RFID technology is not a line of sight technology as far as this object is within the range
of the reader.
The object is able to identify the reader, and it's able to send the feedback single back to the reader.
So using this RFID technology, we can track even multiple objects at the same time.
So what's inside the RFID system?
So as discussed, the RFID system contains two components RFID reader and the RFID tag.
Now these RFID tags are also coming.
In many ways.
This RFID tag could be an active tag.
It could be a passive tag, or it could be a semi passive tag BP as we have seen earlier.
This passive tag does not have their own power supply.
So this passive tag relies on the radio waves, which is coming from the RFID reader for the source
of energy, while in a case of a semi passive tag or a battery assisted tags, they used to have their
own power supply, but for transmitting the feedback signal back to the RFID reader, they used to rely
on the signal which is coming from the RFID reader, while in case of an active tag they used to have
their own power supply, but for transmitting the signal back to the reader, they are relying on their
own power supply.
So as this passive tag do not have their own power supply, the range is less compared to the active
and semi passive tags.
Now let us see what's inside the RFID reader.
So these RFID readers are coming in many sizes and shapes.
So this RFID reader could be your handheld reader.
Or it could be as large as the size of the door, which normally we see inside the shopping mall.
So what's inside an RFID reader?
This area for the reader mainly consists of three components, as you can see here.
So the first component of the RFID reader is the RF signal generator.
So this signal generator generates radio waves which are transmitting using this antenna also to receive
the feedback signal which is coming from the tag, the RFID reader also have a receiver or signal detector.
And to process the information which is being sent by the RFID reader.
I mean, sorry, I mean the RFID tag.
This RFID reader also have a microcontroller.
Or many times this RFID reader is directly connected to the computer.
So what about the RFID tags?
Most of the tags which are being used today are passive tags, because these passive tags are quite
cheaper compared to the active tags as well as they do not require any power source.
They are quite compact, so these passive tags are also coming in many forms.
This passive tag could be either the size of a keychain, or it could be the size of a credit card.
Or maybe it could be in a form of label.
So let us see what's the basic component inside this RFID tag?
So the first component that you see inside RFID tag is a transponder.
Which receives the radio waves which are coming from the reader and send the feedback signal back to
the reader.
As the passive tags do not have their own power supply, they rely on the radio waves which are coming
from the reader, so they use to get the energy from the radio waves which are coming from the reader.
So using this rectifier circuit in here, the energy that is coming from the radio waves is stored across
the capacitor, and this energy is used as a supply for the controller as well as the memory element
inside the RFID tag.
So what about the frequency of operation?
Mainly this RFID tags operates in three frequencies the low frequency range, the high frequency range
and the ultra high frequency range.
So this frequency range of operation varies with country to country.
But majority of the countries used to follow this frequency for the operation of the RFID tags.
So at this low frequency signals can travel very short distance.
The range of RFID tag which is using this low frequency range is up to ten centimeters.
The high frequency radio waves can travel up to one metre, while the ultra high frequency radio waves
can travel much longer.
So RFID tags using the this ultra high frequency can travel up to ten or to to 15m.
This part is very important to to understand how an RFID tags works.
So now let us see the working principle for this RFID tag.
This working principle also depends upon the frequency of operation.
So for the Lf and the HF I mean low frequency and the high frequency operation, the working principle
is basically is based on the inductive coupling.
While in case of ultra high RFID tags the working principle is based on the electromagnetic coupling.
So first let's see the working principle for this Lf and hf RFID tags.
Sorry.
When I see when I say lf I mean low frequency.
And when I say HF, I mean high frequency.
So regarding the inductive coupling near field coupling, as I said earlier, this RFID reader continuously
is continuously sending a radio wave with a particular frequency.
So now this radio waves, which is being sent by this RFID reader, serves three purposes.
First, it induces the enough power into the passive tag.
Second, it provides the synchronization clock.
Third, it acts as a carrier for the data, which is coming back from the RFID tag.
So these are the three basic purposes, which is being served by the radio waves that is sent by this
RFID reader.
So in case of Lf and HF operation as an RFID reader and Tag are very close to each other, the working
principle is based on the inductive coupling.
So the field which is generated by this RFID reader used to get coupled with the antenna of the RFID
tag.
And because this mutual coupling, the voltage will get induced across the coil of RFID tag.
Now some portion of this voltage is getting rectified and used as a power supply for the controller
as well as the memory elements.
Now, as the RFID reader is sending a radio wave of a particular frequency.
So the voltage that is induced across the coil is also of a particular frequency.
So this induced voltage is also used to derive the synchronization clock for the controller.
So now let us suppose if we connect a load of the coil, then current will start flowing through this
load.
And if we change the impedance of this load, then the current that is flowing through this load will
also change of course.
So now let us suppose if we switch on and off this load then the current will also switch on and off.
So this switching of current or rate of change of current also generates a voltage in an RFID reader.
So this is switching on and off of the.
The load is known as the load modulation.
Please remind this term the load modulation.
This term I will detail it.
I will present it in the next in the next session, which is regarding the communication between the
reader and the cart.
The load module modulation is the key of the communication.
Please remind this term because we will need it for later.
So now let us suppose if we switch on and off this load according to the data that is stored inside
this RFID tag, then that data can be read by the RFID reader in the form of a voltage.
So in this way, using this load modulation, we are changing the voltage that is generated across RFID
reader coil.
And in this way we are generating modulation on a carrier frequency.
Also this term you need to remind it very well carrier frequency.
We will need it for for the for the next session.
Our carrier frequency will be 1350 six megahertz.
Please remind this part then in this way in a low frequency and the high frequency RFID tag, using
this load modulation technique, the data is being sent back to the RFID reader.
What about the far field coupling?
So now let us see the working principle for the ultra high frequency.
In case of UHF ultra high frequency, as the distance between the reader and the tag is up to few meters,
the coupling between the reader and the coil will be the far field coupling.
This RFID reader is continuously, as you can see here, is continuously sending the radio waves of
a particular frequency towards the tag.
And in response, the stack is sending a weak signal to the RFID reader.
So, as you may know, our tag is here.
Okay.
Uh, now, this weak signal which is being sent back to the RFID reader, is known as the backscatter
scene.
And the intensity of this backscattered signal depends upon the load matching across the coil.
So if the load is matched exactly, then the intensity of the backscattered signal will be more.
But if the load is not matched exactly that the then the intensity of this backscattered signal will
be less.
So in this way, by changing the condition of a load, we can change the intensity of this backscattered
signal.
And if we change the condition of a load according to the data that is being stored across this RFID
tag, then that data can be sent back to the RFID reader.
So in this way, a RFID reader is able to sense that data.
Now, in case of a powerful coupling, as the distance between the RFID reader and tag is a few meters,
the initial signal which is being sent by the reader should be strong so that the backscattered signal
can be retrieved by this RFID reader.
So this is how, in case of a far field coupling, the signal is sent back to the RFID reader using
the Backscattered modulation technique.
So now I will talk to you in the next session.